♪ ♪ ♪
Hi, it's Dessi Zaharieva and I'm here to talk to you about how
the same exercise type might lead to different glucose outcomes.
A little about me:
I'm a Certified Exercise Physiologist, Diabetes Educator and Researcher,
and have been living with Type One Diabetes myself for over 28 years.
Today we'll chat about why the same activity can
affect your glucose levels differently depending on
how hard you're working or the situation you're in.
♪ ♪ ♪
How hard you're working or the intensity of an activity
may cause different responses to your glucose levels.
Here are some considerations:
Low to moderate intensity activities like brisk walking
or running may cause your glucose levels to drop.
Mixed intensity activities like soccer or CrossFit
may cause your glucose levels to go up or down,
depending on how much of that activity is high
intensity versus low to moderate intensity.
To learn more about mixed intensity exercise and how to prepare
for it, listen to our episode on mixed intensity exercise.
High intensity activities like explosive sprinting, especially
while fasting may cause your glucose levels to rise.
♪ ♪ ♪
Let's discuss the science behind it.
During low intensity activities like walking,
fat is the body's preferred fuel source.
As the intensity of exercise increases, like jogging or
running, the body relies on fat and carbs for energy.
Your liver will release glucose into the bloodstream
to try and match what the muscles are using,
but it typically can't keep up with the
glucose demand of those working muscles.
This is why you often need to eat extra
carbs before or during a run to avoid lows.
Another option is to turn on a Tidepool Loop activity preset
an hour before exercise starts to let the app know that
you need less insulin than usual when you begin exercise.
For high intensity exercise like explosive sprinting or power
lifting your body typically relies more on carbs for fuel,
which means your muscles break down stored glycogen,
your body's form of stored carbs, for quick energy,
while your liver releases more glucose into the bloodstream.
However, your muscles can't keep up with the amount of
glucose, and this often leads to a rise in glucose levels.
In the Tidepool Loop app, the presets for exercise
section includes a tool to help you understand how the
intensity of an activity might affect your glucose levels.
Why context matters:
The situation you're in can also change how
an activity affects your glucose levels.
Let's use swimming as an example.
During swim practice, when you're swimming laps, you might
see similar changes or drops in your glucose levels each week.
But on a competition day with adrenaline pumping friends and family
cheering you on, and the pressure to win glucose levels may rise.
More specifically during competition stress hormones like
adrenaline and cortisol are released signaling to the liver
to release glucose to the bloodstream to provide quick energy.
In individuals with Type One Diabetes, this response
is not balanced by an appropriate increase in insulin,
therefore, often leading to a rise in glucose levels.
Additionally, adrenaline can reduce muscle glucose
uptake by making the cells less sensitive to insulin.
This combination of increased glucose production by the
liver and reduced uptake by the muscles can result in
hyperglycemia or high glucose levels during intense exercise.
So what do you do in these situations?
Remember, you might need different strategies depending on your situation.
Regular practices may require less insulin, or you may
need extra carbs on hand to reduce the risk of lows.
But on game day, monitor your glucose levels and be
aware that your body may not need less insulin and
more carbs like you've often done on practice days.
I'd love to share a personal example.
I had been training TaeKwonDo for over 15 years and qualified
to represent Team Canada at the World Championships.
I had spent countless hours in practice and attending local competitions.
I was familiar with how my glucose levels responded
during practice or even smaller competitions.
Usually with practice, my glucose levels stayed
pretty stable or dropped from many hours of activity.
But when I competed at my very first TaeKwonDo World Championships
for Team Canada, everything changed. Before the competition
my glucose levels were steady around 180 milligrams
per deciliter, and I felt pretty good, albeit nervous.
After my first match, which lasted less than 10
minutes, my glucose levels rose to the four hundreds.
The adrenaline impact was so real.
♪ ♪ ♪
Before we wrap up, let's take 15 minutes this week to notice how
exercise intensity and context might affect your glucose levels.
Here are a few things to explore:
Do your glucose levels respond differently
during practices versus games or races?
How does increasing or decreasing the intensity
of an activity affect your glucose levels?
What happens to your glucose levels when you
do walking versus running versus sprinting?
If you play competitive sports, try visualizing
the event to prepare yourself for game day.
Imagine you're stepping into the competition ring
or on the field, whatever that may be for you.
Repeat this at the end of every practice for five to 10 minutes if you can.
This might help you handle stressful situations better because
you've already been there in your mind and prepared for this moment.
Understanding these differences can help you plan better for
physical activity and manage your glucose levels more effectively.
♪ ♪ ♪